# Hamel Husain



hamel.husain@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/hamelhusain



214-893-3072



https://hamel.dev

### Summary

I enjoy building tools and platforms to make data scientists more successful. I have authored and am a core maintainer of many popular open source data science tools / infrastructure. I also have extensive experience as a machine learning engineer across a wide variety of industries.

Professional Page: https://hamel.dev/

## **Experience**



### Creating Amazing Tools For Data Scientists

Sep 2020 - Present (7 months +)

Work with Jeremy Howard on various open-source projects. My focus is on infrastructure, developer tools, DevOps, and software engineering.

Some products I've been involved with so far:

- nbdev: A notebook-enabled software development environment github.com/fastai/nbdev
- fastcore: Extensions to the python programming language github.com/fastai/fastcore
- ghapi: A python client for the GitHub API w/ support for GitHub Actions github.com/fastai/ghapi
- fastpages: A blogging platform with support for Jupyter notebooks github.com/fastai/fastpages

I've also created and help maintain many of the CI, integration tests, and build tools for the fastai ecosystem. Some examples include Conda build tooling https://github.com/fastai/fastconda, Docker image maintenance https://github.com/fastai/docker-containers, and many others.

# Staff Machine Learning Engineer

GitHub

2017 - Present (4 years 3 months +)

- Creating systems and conducting research that enable representation learning of code, issues, repos, and users.
- Led launch of CodeSearchNet (www.github.com/github/CodeSearchNet)
- Building a new class of Machine Learning Ops products: https://www.mlops-github.com

Open sourced several examples of how to build data products and use deep learning with public GitHub data. These examples can be viewed at: http://hamel.dev, and include

- Summarizing GitHub Issues using sequence to sequence models
- Natural Language Semantic Code Search
- How to create machine learning enabled GitHub Apps to automate the developer workflow
- How to achieve Machine Learning Ops with GitHub Actions and Kubeflow

#### Airbnb

2016 - 2017 (2 years)

- Led the creation of a company-wide machine learning infrastructure roadmap.
- Optimized marketing spend of \$500M annually using machine learning.
- Built customer lifetime value models that predict spending patterns for every user at an individual level. This is used across the entire company in the following areas: marketing, customer service, risk and finance.
- Created image classification models to recognize objects in listing photos and for image re-ordering.
- Built end-to-end pipelines for data products using Airflow.
- Created reusable frameworks and infrastructure that enable other data scientists to iterate faster.
- Used a large suite of tools for modeling: Spark, Python, Keras / TensorFlow, DataRobot, H2o, Vowpal Wabbit.

# Senior Data Scientist

#### **DataRobot**

2015 - 2016 (2 years)

Data scientist and product manager for a machine-learning software company.

- Deployed a wide variety of modern algorithms such as xgboost, random forest, gradient boosted trees, support vector machines, elastic net etc. on operational systems.
- Regularly utilized python, spark and H2O for data wrangling, model building and visualizations.
- Built data science workflows in order to ensure that data was aggregated, collected and cleaned in ways that maximized accuracy and transparency.
- Contributed significantly to the product design and user experience for the data ingest and python API components of the product.
- Benchmarked and studied competing and complimentary machine learning software for accuracy, speed and usability. (H20, Graphlab/Turi, Amazon, Azure, etc.)
- Contribute to product strategy and roadmap.
- Presently an advisor on product strategy and data science.

# VP, Applied Analytics

#### **AlixPartners**

2011 - 2015 (5 years)

Led data science efforts on consulting engagements for a wide variety of industries. Some concrete outcomes:

- Founding member of the advanced analytics consulting practice, grew a team of 5 to 50 machine learning and analytics practitioners.
- Built data-driven tools that enabled a large restaurant chain reduce food-waste by 15% through demand forecasting.
- Created models and interactive data visualizations for a large casino to increase the detection of fraud by 50%.
- Performed market basket analysis and built recommendation systems that increased conversion rate by 5% for a large clothing retailer.
- Launched professional development curriculum for junior data scientists that built skills for data wrangling, predictive modeling and visualizations using Python and the command line.

# > Consultant - Management Consulting

#### Accenture

2004 - 2008 (5 years)

Specialized in CRM data analysis for fortune 500 telecommunications companies. Lead teams of 3-5 people on multiple engagements to implement data analytics solutions for clients in the telecom industry. Saved clients over \$85M dollars in the areas of supply chain, call center optimization and churn reduction.

#### Some examples include:

- Provided early detection of product defects and network failures through use of call center analytics, saving over \$10M in contact center overhead.
- Built predictive models to provide an early warning system for customer churn, allowing client to intervene and reduce churn rate by 7%.
- Developed scorecards, metrics, and dashboards that enabled clients to increase customer satisfaction while simultaneously reducing costs by changing employee and partner incentive structures.

# & Credit Risk Analyst

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

May 2003 - Apr 2004 (1 year)

Developed and implemented models to evaluate credit risk on loan portfolios.

### **Education**



### **Georgia Institute of Technology**

Master of Science (M.S.), Computer Science, Machine Learning

# M

# **University of Michigan**

Doctor of Law (J.D.), Cum Laude

Graduated, but I decided to not pursue a career in law and instead follow my passion for data science and machine learning.



### Southern Methodist University

B.S., Mathematics and Industrial Engineering

Senior Design Project- Airline Ticket Counter Staff Forecasting and Planning Model: http://lyle.smu.edu/emis/design/?p=641